[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
all right enough of that nonsense let's
begin
welcome everyone to the stoa i'm peter
limberg the steward of the stoa and the
stowe is a place for us to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
knife's
edge of this very moment for the new
faces here the stoa
um it's like a digital campfire we call
it a communal podcast sometimes we have
a wisdom gym
we have hundreds of events uh that have
been happening since kovic came online
um and we invite part of the events we
invite interesting people to come in to
share their ideas and we have a
collective conversation with them
uh and today we have chris gabriel um
from meme analysis uh for those of you
don't know
this is a really cool uh youtube channel
that's been gaining in popularity
and it's the title basically says it uh
he analyzes memes
that are happening floating around in
the noah sphere
um so and today he's going to talk about
the occult
so how today is going to work i'm going
to hand it over to chris in a moment and
he's going to share his thoughts on
the topic at hand uh and if you have any
questions
throughout put them in the chat box put
a cue or question before it
uh and then i will call on you you'll
mute yourself you ask your question to
chris
you want me to read it on your behalf
because this will go on youtube just
indicate that in the chats
so i think that's everything um chris
how you doing today my friend
you're on mute yeah all right doing good
doing good i wasn't sure if i could undo
it
um i'm doing very well thank you for
having me on peter it's a pleasure i'm
glad you're
you're here um so yeah i think i'll just
uh
hand it over to you and then let me know
when uh you like me to jump in
all right so the presentation is good
okay so i thought it would start with a
story
that i think illustrates the point that
we are at now
better than any other and that is
the pre-islamic world
now before muhammad
was visited by gabriel the mecca which
is the big black cube
that i'm sure everybody has seen before
muhammad there were thousands
of gods that were worshiped at mecca
thousands of tiny little idols
and each one you know merchants had
their own little god
that they worshipped each worshipped at
their own
tiny gods some even just gin spirits
there is no unifying
force there is no unifying belief there
is just countless
individual uh spirits vying for
supremacy
in this uh very diverse culture
it's a culture of merchants and so
muhammad is himself a merchant after
being visited by gabriel
he you know realizes the message
of allah the one true god goes back to
mecca and destroys
all of the idols and establishes just
one
this is where we're at we have in we
have the almost the reverse
where we went from many being funneled
into one
meme in the wake of the death of god
in the nietzschean sense we have been
left with many tiny little pieces
attempting to assert themselves
as a symbolic language christianity over
the past 2000 years
served as the ultimate symbolic form
which is why
if you read literature it is filled with
illusions in reference to christianity
because that is the shared symbolic
language so
in christianity's absence in god's
absence
we have innumerable attempts at
a unified symbolic language and memes
represent
these attempts so what is a meme
it's you know it's a word that has very
definitely been maligned it's just
thought of as a silly internet joke
but it is certainly more than that um
memes
to me are archetypes and symbols in the
jungian sense
which is to say that they are vessels
for
archaic energies psychic energy
and through making you know through the
vessel being
unassailable to reason that's why
they're funny
if we could think about them they
wouldn't be funny just like if you could
clearly see any given symbol it would
lose its efficacy
so memes are archetypal symbols and
something that young talked about that
is not recognized often
is that archetypes are not stagnant
you hear a lot of people talk about
archetypes and if even
even teachers teaching about archetypes
they say kind of like they're stock
characters like they're the same thing
forever they've been the same thing from
you know 2000 to 240
to 2020 and it's not true if you read
young you see that they have transformed
every generation to make themselves
as efficient as possible the vessel
is changing but the energy is the same
it's an archetypal energy that
expresses itself through forms
and while one might be tempted to say in
this age of reason that we live that
we've gotten rid of all
of our little beliefs and all of our
symbols we haven't
they've gone into hiding in the form of
memes
which is why we laugh at them we are
able to laugh
there's a really wonderful story about a
rabbi
a a man goes to visit his rabbi and says
in the past so many men
spoke to god so many men saw
god nowadays nobody does
why is that and the rabbi says today
nobody bows low enough
so to try and gain insight into the
collective unconscious
i am bowing as low as i can and i am
looking at memes i'm looking at perhaps
a great
sewer of information and i'm trying to
make sense of it i'm trying to see the
meaning
in all of these expressions so
beyond just being an archetypal symbol
because what does that mean
we have to look at the idea that
we have a lot of information in the
world you have a lot of information
just like we have a lot of idols and we
compress them they're condensed into
one perfect form memes take a lot of
information
archetypes take a lot of information and
condense it into a transmittable form
the cross for example is christianity
without the cross there is no
christianity it is the
sublime symbol and so
this is what memes do as well they take
a lot of cultural information
even a lot of personal information and
they transform it into a
single easily understood image
and of course many memes play off of
this they make it very complex
or you know intentionally obtuse there's
no way to
to get the meaning out of it um but at
its
at its very root a meme is simply an
image or a symbol or a word that
condenses lots of
ideas and lots of context into a single
form
some really good examples of this would
be kilroy was here
which is a a popular piece of graffiti
from world war
ii um it's a man looking over a wall and
his nose is hanging down
uh in britain this was no sugar
but in america it's uh it's kill robes
here
another good example of a graffiti one
is
uh john michelle basquiat's samo
samo copyright is a kind of
god that he invented uh with a friend
and they would spray
painted all over new york and everybody
knew samoa everybody saw
samo but nobody knew basquiat but
basquiat was able to attain
fame because of the energy that he had
harnessed through the popularity of samo
also important is one that everybody
recognizes
everybody knows spider-man
everybody does the spider-man hands you
know that this is web
shooting or even uh dr strange does it
too ditko
knew that he had something good in the
spider-man
hand symbol i'm sure you see every kid
in america every kid in the world who's
seen a spider-man movie does that
wanting to sling webs that is an
effective symbol
because it inspires repetition it takes
something really interesting something
supernatural
which is web slinging and then every kid
wants to do that that's another good
yeah spock
you take an alien with superpowers and
he makes a symbol and if you learn to do
it
every kid wants to do it because every
kid wants power
it takes a knowledge of comics it takes
a knowledge of television
and then also important now we get into
the occultism
because we've talked about young and
talked about it but we have to see the
occultism applied
and we see that in v for victory
and peace now churchill utilized v
for victory to empower britain's
symbolism
but what many don't know is that
aleister crowley actually
invented v for victory as a weapon
against the nazi's swastika
the swastika is a reversed solar symbol
which is why many now use the black sun
because the black sun
is another reversed solar symbol
and the solar god or at least in this
context
is uh ra and
who who is able to attack ra
is seth apophis and his symbol
is v because he's a destroyer he cuts
um in a video i'd actually explained how
rock paper scissors is a
symbolic game and one of the oldest
games ever played
but that is a magical usage that's why
that's such a powerful symbol
and of course the swastika is still
powerful
the swastika is still one of the most
powerful symbols because you know you
see somebody wearing it and you know
what it means
you know what that symbol means um and
the same goes
for racial slurs they condense a culture
of you know of of racism and of
historical oppression into a single word
which is why those words are so
sensitive and so powerful
um but this idea of a sensitive of a
powerful image and a powerful word
um does not have its roots really in
dawkins richard dawkins who coined the
term
meme it goes much farther back
and it's almost always to occultists
it is an intrinsically occult idea
we find it in um elifus levi
uh levi talks about how
ideas are oftentimes more infectious
than
diseases themselves he describes
uh his occult vision is one of a world
as
will he was influenced by schopenhauer
directly in fact
and he viewed diseases of will as
diseases
spread through images and words
and fads and he said that you know they
spread faster than cholera
before that we have abramolin who is one
of them
again another very famous magician and
his his rituals were very popular in the
golden dawn
and he said directly in his book do not
leave this book open
if a child a woman or an uninitiated man
sees one of these symbols they're going
to be infected and they're going to
start drawing it
and they're going to unconsciously give
power to whatever the symbol meant
so it was occultists that have known
throughout all of time
that images and words have power
uh it's not just a modern pop science
idea
but i would say that the true inheritor
of the meme concept is william s
burroughs who in the 50s and 60s
really does the leg work in developing
the idea of a
viral infectious image or word
i'm sure if you've read burrows you're
familiar with the idea of a word
virus a word virus
is uh able to spread person to person
and he even says language is a virus
from outer space he does not think
language
is innately human but it's a it's a
virus that came to
manipulate human evolution and i think
that there's something i think that's
a very a very fascinating and useful
idea if we look at language simply as a
natural expression
we miss out on just how bizarre it can
be
so his word viruses and image viruses
were
capable of influencing the body you know
it goes beyond
simply um an idea it's not just mental
and it wasn't mental for occultists
either these infectious ideas
did in fact affect the body that's a
very tough idea
but through wilhelm reich who's one of
my very favorites
he developed um character armor
he was the creator of vegeta therapy
and orgone he was a student of freud
he was such a fan of
freud's libido found it to be such
a brilliant idea that he was very
disappointed when freud
no longer centered his thought on libido
and he sought to correct that and
developed his concept of orgone energy
which takes the freudian libido and puts
it in a mass
almost a cosmic context in which
creation and destruction are the
expressions of
that universal ocean of will or drive
which is present in nietzsche and
schopenhauer
so his focus on the way that
ideas and neuroses affect the body which
freud had in his concept of
hysteria which is why we have little
ticks or why we have little uh twitches
that is the effect of an idea of
something mental
on the body so
it's even now we get into the really
scary stuff which is an idea that you
see out in public or in a movie or in a
meme
because memes do spread ideology they
spread neuroses
and if you get infected your bodily
sensations will shift your bodily
perceptions
of the world are altered and you are
contorted in accordance with those ideas
one would never say that the ideal of
fitness does not
inspire a reaction in the sense
you know you witness ideals and you
attempt to replicate them or to go away
from them those
are ideas that directly affect your body
you can get much worse than that but
i'm not going to focus too much on the
body
but somebody who did who took these
ideas these old occult ideas
is l ron hubbard the creator of
scientology and dianetics
one of his threats is reliant on the
idea of a word virus
he often would say that if you found out
the secrets of scientology too early
you would get cancer just by hearing the
words
if you hear the ideas that are present
in higher level
scientology you will die this was
accepted and this is
a major part of the scientological canon
is if you say the right words you can
kill people
if you make the right images you know
uh hubbard claimed that he he developed
the perfect method of photography
that it was like purely satisfying it
was the ultimate way to photograph
things
um this corresponded to what he called
the reactive mind and the reactive mind
is
really just the freudian unconscious and
what he called the symbols and the
viruses within it are
engrams engrams are an older idea from a
guy named
seaman actually and
he developed his concept of the mnemonic
the neemi which is just a store of
biological memories
it's a precursor to the unconscious
but we see like all of this and also
just
i guess i skipped that and i i don't
know how many of you know if you're into
hubbard you probably know that he was
learned in
aleister crowley's system of thelmic
magic
and that he was good friends for a bit
with jack parsons
who is directly one of crowley's
students and developed a lot of american
thelma and also formed jet propulsion
labs
and was one of the pioneering rocket
scientists
using magic he did this uh hubbard
kind of stole his wife and stole tens of
thousands of dollars from him
but before that they were good friends
and did magic together
and so hubbard took all of his magical
knowledge
hubbard's son even attests to saying
that um
hubbard the only part of his system that
works
is alistair crowley's it's black magic
so the parts of dianetics that work
are magical ideas those are infectious
words that exist in the unconscious that
are repressed
and that affect our bodies these are all
very important
but i'm sure many of you have come here
looking for internet memes
because that's how you know the word we
know the word from the internet
and so what's the most important
internet meme it's from the song
that peter played before we were talking
that is chabylee chatelet
pepe and his god
form of cac now cac
is widely maligned i think
as a kind of far-right idea as a
far-right
symbol but he's far more than that and
it's a mistake to politicize
symbolism and of course we're living in
an
era of politicized symbolism but to do
so is to deny
much of its power politics is almost
antithetical to real power
which is symbolic power but keck
is the form of pepe as a god
pepe is initially um a frog from a comic
by matt fury
i think it's called boys club and he is
just a
happy little frog um and one of the
lines that he has is
feels good man uh one of you mentioned
the documentary
in uh in the comments um he says feels
good man and this meme
did well it took an image of pepe from
feels good man everything from boys club
with that quote
and it does well on the internet it's a
reaction image
catches on well enough his image is
effective it speaks to the unconscious
the idea of a frog with feelings
speaks to the collective unconscious in
this very specific way
and so all kinds of people on the
internet start making their own drawings
of him
and this gives way over time
to him becoming a very chaotic uh
violent brutal character contrasted
with wojak who is sad he is
the face when no gf he is the face one
no girlfriend he is the sad fellow
the much more human character and
i thought back in 2016 well this is
perfectly nietzsche's
apollonian and dionysian dichotomy a
beastly wild man and a saddened
fantasy a dreamer
human so what would become of this kind
of chaotic
character this chaotic monster man
so just to do a little bit of symbolic
play we take um
the dionysian young saw the dionysian in
odin
and who does odin correspond with but
hermes
so we find
a hermetic character in cac
in this god form of pepe who
speaks to people on 4chan through
repeated numbers
and of course repeating numbers are a
major part of the occult
specifically in kabbalah kabbalistic
numerology
it uh it is the the word of god
understood through numerology through
repeated numbers and numbers
um patterns so kex speaks in these
number patterns
dubs and trips and quads which is a
number that comes
with every post on 4chan and it might
have a repeating number
and that is how you knew that keck was
speaking through that user
anybody could be a vessel of this
archetype
and so it became very very popular many
people were doing the will of this god
because
of course they actually saw he had an
effect on them
he was actually doing something and
that's one of the problems with these
old dead gods
these old religious systems it's almost
impossible to
feel their effect on us
we feel as if these gods are dead but
you
you go with keck he's a living god and
he's influencing you
as you as you pray as you worship him
and all it takes is using the internet
and so synchronicities start arising
from this worship
which is chatelai it's a song that has a
frog with a magic wand
and i think the artist is pepe and that
was like
that was a huge affirmation like oh my
you know
we were waiting to exist this record
is made for us it was made for us
we were destined to be and that is in
fact the case i think
any archetype in its dignified power
begins to emit synchronicities which is
kind of meaningful coincidences
archetypes are the vector of these
synchronicities
as young saw it so
internet memes if they are popular
enough
are given a kind of vast magical power
because they are where the archetype is
most intense
it's an intensity of archetypal value
on a meme which is shared by a lot of
strangers
it lacks much of the trouble of an
actual culture
of a physical culture there's no
infighting for the most part
it's a clear mass and an anonymous mass
so mass mindedness is just
the rule so
we we see the ideas from occultists
are being proven day by day in the form
of memes
we have lots of new memes that are very
popular words
ideas that are extremely potent
and almost irrational if you bring it up
you can't have rational conversation
about these ideas
that's how you know it's really
important that it's a meme
and that it exists in the unconscious if
you could talk rationally about
something
you could take it apart but if you get
into a conversation with somebody and
use
they call them buzzwords you use a
buzzword and it just
instantly enrages somebody that's how
you know it's a meme
that it has a major unconscious value
and that you're not going to be able to
discuss it it's it's far beyond the
realm of conscious discussion
the ego the self is not involved that is
a pure
that is a purely unconscious discussion
that's going to occur
what is the way out it's difficult to
say i think
a lot of conscious attention paying
attention
to memes and that is why my motto on my
channel is
memes matter if you can just take that
step to say
memes matter that this word this idea
this image
this political concept this character
they matter it's not just uh it's not
real but it's also not something that's
senseless
it matters it has power
that is the first step to having real
discussions and real progress
and not ever remaining possessed by
these forces which really are
playing with us you can make you know
you can make up
these uh you can make up a whole
population and you introduce ideas and
you witness them tear each other apart
that is what archetypes autonomous
forces do for fun
we are at the whim of these irrational
powerful ideas
and to combat it we just have to realize
that it goes on
that there are ideas that are beyond our
conscious
attention and that they affect us
and that is basically it memes matter
cool it means matter um so start
throwing your questions in the chat
uh i'll i'll warm chris up with a few
questions on my own
so uh angela nagle is a kill on normies
book
she sort of maps out how
sort of the trollish reactionary uh
memes were
emerged on the chance and uh sort of the
social justice memes uh emerge on tumblr
so i'm curious if you have any thoughts
as to that
and the somewhat adjacent related
question is um
uh john michael greer that druid uh he
was on daniel thornson's uh
podcast it was a really great great
episode and uh he was talking about kind
of like
pepe and how that came online and the
chance and all that kind of like
all that strangeness was occurring and
he says people are becoming conscious of
it using these memes as sigils
uh and then in the next election there's
gonna be uh
basically magic warfare uh you know to
fight for the the
collective mind and the nose here um
and yeah so and then i was gonna slip in
some like the left can't mean
uh so who you think would win in that
kind of warfare if that happening that
that is happening on a conscious level
um so yeah i'll just throw that at you
so
[Music]
i'll go with the left cam meme for now
since that was that's a powerful one
that's an important one
um i think unfortunately there is
something to it at the moment
and that is because right-wing ideas
um speak to the lowest part of humanity
they speak to the shadow they speak to
repressed
emotions and those are emotions that
desperately want to express themselves
they want to come out
so that's why a right-wing meme
can just be a picture and the n-word and
that is a cathartic release
for far-right people um and that's in a
way it's just it's a cathartic release
for anybody who has
a concept of the significance of the
word
just by putting a taboo onto a word you
inspire the opposite you inspire
a virulent desire to abuse
so when the left makes its arguments
from a position
of um rationality which is always a
mistake politics is not rational and you
shouldn't try to make it something it's
not it's theater
it's always been theater if you're not
entertaining you can't win
so this idea that we can argue from a
a secular viewpoint is impossible
i think that this is the real problem
with marx
he is too materialist for his own good
you know
even if i don't know even if we could
objectively prove that material causes
were actually the engine of history it
would still not be a convincing argument
for most people it still wouldn't work
because it doesn't speak to the
unconscious this is what
wilhelm reich does correctly he
introduces
orgone energy into the equation
introducing freudian ideas to marx
elevates both and even more so mark
fisher
he has the idea of acid communism of a
psychedelic communism which is really
just
religious meaningful communism that is
the only way that the left
could mean is by introducing something
meaningful
the right has everything they have
paganism they have christianity they
have islam
even judaism they have all the religions
because every religion that has been has
been conservative to a modern viewpoint
so they play with conservative ideas and
they they
prance about with them they don't
believe in them but they play with it
because that's all you need to do to
have
meaningful intercourse online
the left is too committed to rational
ideals
to actually make any any way
in progress with the people with the
masses the masses are irrational
and must be spoken to symbolically
um the john michael greer i was actually
referencing his translation of the book
of abramelin
when i was talking about the uh the
images the sigils that can become
infected how they infect people so i am
familiar with his work
i didn't watch phil's good man yet but
my friend worked on it so i'm like
waiting to see it but and also what i
would share
if you watched feels good man you saw
the the pepe auction
and i have a book from the pepe auction
it's got
all of the rare pepes
um that had one that sold for thirty
nine thousand dollars
at the auction the rarest pepe
but as for what made pepe arise i think
it was i think as we attempt to be more
and more civilized we attempt to be
rationalistic
again you inspire the opposite you
inspire a chaotic
dionysian force in man that wishes to
awaken
it wants to wake up and the more that we
repress our shadow
as something that is not us that's the
other that's other people
that's those poor people or that's those
you know those those trashy people
they're the ones these
these deplorable people or the these uh
you know stupid
libertards it's those people that have
the bad stuff
it denies that all of that everything
you see and others that you despise is
just your own
it is a mass projection and an inability
to unify
the self uh and this is of course the
whole point of politics
is just all right let's split it off and
we fight the opposite as hard as we can
no there's no there's no thought to it
there's no reason to it and
there can't be um
sorry what was what was another point
what was another question
um so who would win that kind of the the
spiritual warfare that's occurring
between the left and right and the other
one is uh how they emerge in different
platforms and like the tumblr
social justice and then and i i would i
would say i'm surprised that um
you're saying that left comes from a
rational based argument because some
people would not say that
and then they have like these
shame-based tactics to make you awoke
and all that type of stuff
so i'd throw out that out there as well
they use
irrationality but they are not possessed
by it they are arguing on
a humanistic basis
their origins are christian and
christianity is already a relatively
more rational
religion than or not maybe rational is
not the right word i should say
detached from the body uh
cerebral um
and i mean that in a bad way the body is
the truth
the body is the message and for the left
to
progress they need to find their bodies
again
um as for the and this gets to the point
about the the opposite
in um tumblr you have the 4chan guys and
the tumblr girls and
i knew early on like that these two are
a divine relationship and that they need
to be unified to progress
um for seders which are followers of
dionysus
there are mainad's nymphs
the female followers of dionysus but the
problem is that both are asexual both
have been
totally neutered castrated by the
internet
the internet is the biggest anti-sex
machine imaginable
it exists to suck your libido out
so in the past what would have been a
relationship between
a girl who is today in sjw and a boy who
is
today a far-right internet nazi in the
past
they would have been uh archie and betty
um is it that yeah betty and veronica
that's right betty betty betty okay i
don't know i don't know if you
prefer betty or veronica but either way
they would have been together they would
have been just
a kid couple but because we have the
internet because we have this
this polarizing machine this
machine that rips you out of your body
it rips your libido away from you and
puts you into this
illusion world they only talk to each
other
through that veil and of course you know
there's always been a little bit of
gender war play
it's just the way it is it's part of the
game of sex and mating
but on the internet you only have the
part that's fighting you only have the
part that's conflict and it really kind
of prevents people from actually dating
and actually going out
so i think so much of the problem has to
do with a
lack of sexuality it has to do with a
being neutered by the internet
cool all right on that note let's turn
to the
the q and a's um
[Music]
levi reed you had a question if you can
unmute yourself and ask it to chris
yes um can you hear me all right
uh do you feel ideas require
symbols and memes in order to thrive or
do they
simply exist as a way to spread an idea
or do you feel that they are the
embodiment of the idea itself
that's a good question um and it's tough
to say there are certainly ideas
that don't have memes but i think it
kind of speaks to
one of the big problems in academia
which is that the vast majority of
essays that are ever published are not
read by anybody but the editor of a
journal but
if you have a memetic idea everybody's
going to know about it eventually
so there are ideas that don't have memes
but they're weak
and they don't survive the test of time
no matter how good of an idea it is you
know even if it's an important idea
if it's not an effective virulent idea
if there's not some part of it
that's catchy this won't do
so memes
are symbols that signify the presence of
an old idea
and it kind of gets to the point where
one would imagine there is only a set
amount of ideas in the world
and that all of the archetypes represent
those ideas or that all ideas
are related to those archetypal
expressions
and if your idea is too far away if it's
not close to that intense energy
it'll be forgotten if it's memetic it's
close to the source
cool do you have a follow-up
so you feel that
ideas have to be old in
order for them to be taken
by people in order to become a medic
they have to be
closer to something that is based
exactly and that is why
you have the meme of you know you react
some people they respond to an idea and
they say based
because it is literally a base idea
cool thank you uh evan you're up next
you can and yeah sorry sorry i had to
get unmuted thank you um
so my question is um i kept having the
notion of the concept of memetic hazards
um and the i guess bowstrum or what have
you since um
specifically the idea of cogito hazards
come up for me during your initial
um sort of presentation especially when
you were talking about the
um the sense of the book that you don't
want to leave
open um etc and so i was i was wondering
if you could maybe just riff on
uh talk about the idea of um the
relationship between your conception of
memes and their virality here uh and
whether they're memetically or
cognitively hazardous to us potentially
and
i'm really interested to get your take
on that
yes that's a very important idea to me
um
because i think if you think about it if
you think about memes correctly you
would be afraid and you would recognize
them as hazardous
um you know one of lovecraft's quotes
is is so brilliant and it so brilliantly
speaks to the tr the trouble
in believing in anything which is you
know the most
the most um shoot uh i'm gonna have to
paraphrase it but the most um
fortunate trait in mankind is that we
cannot
um correspond all the parts of our mind
if we were able to actually make sense
of what we believe we would go mad
and this is an idea that crowley talks
about heavily in book four
um and it's said like you know
if you don't know every devil the one
that you've forgotten is going to come
up from behind you and strangle you to
death
so he says you know if most christians
could actually reason out
what they believe which is to say if you
really think that
if you don't save somebody that they are
going to go to hell
how do you sleep at night knowing that
the majority of humans are going to be
tortured for eternity
you simply can't really believe it
without that um distance without that
cognitive
dissonance from the belief if you
actually believe the thing
wholeheartedly you would go mad
but the dangerous part of the cognitive
hazard is that when you do
start to treat it as it is when you
if you have a really bad idea or a
really bad idea gets you
and you live according to it then you're
you're lost
like there's a lot of in-cell propaganda
and it is impossible to get through to
these people like
they are wholeheartedly believers in
this idea because it was such a
a hazardous effective idea it just traps
them
for good and it contorts your body you
you act insecure it makes you insecure
it makes you
despise your body there's a lot of ideas
like this
so i definitely think that mimetic
hazards
cognitive hazards are not just a product
of fiction
they are real and they are a major part
of modern life
i'm curious um what's your thoughts on q
anon
uh because i've been studying the um
culture war
when i go on to the chance man it's like
my body just shrivels down i can't stay
on there too long
but just i have a feel of the contours
of the different mimetic mean plexus out
there
and it's a very distinct one from kind
of the trollish reactionary sphere
but they're kind of in the same sandbox
and chance uh
how do you read that movement and with
the kind of the lens of the archetypes
and the memes
so i'm of two minds i'm of the i'm of
the magical mind and i am of the
human all-too-human mind and that
humanoid it's a human part man
i really feel bad for them i really pity
them but that's
that's a bad way to look at it you look
at it like a magician you say yes
we're so close now if i made the right
stupid little post i could gain as much
power
as q that was so darn
easy to create a new cult a new religion
and i mean it is it is a serious cult
like
there's a lot of sad very very very very
sad groups of q people talking about how
they've lost their families you know
they've alienated themselves
from all their friends and family and i
think that is such
a miserable idea you know
the really important idea that nietzsche
and max sterner talk about and these are
like serious serious individualists
is that you know if you are detaching
from friends
you're making a huge mistake you know if
your ideas
alienate you from your friends you
you have gone too far and i think that
there's something to that of course i
think sometimes we need
to assert what we believe is really
important
but darn we live in a time where people
are so desperate for meaning
they're so desperate for the truth and
conspiracies offer a memetic form of
truth where instead of a religion where
you need ritual
you need um you know you need to
actually engage in a text
in conspiracies you take the red pill it
is as simple as
one post one video one meme even and
you'll be converted
you will have witnessed the truth like
neo you'll see the matrix
but my biggest question is this
you've taken the red pill you've woken
up you were like neo
what changes what now neo entered a new
world and you know
felt his body again when you believe
in a conspiracy
what changes does your day-to-day life
change
if not what's the [ __ ] point you know
it's it's purely a ki
and this is the real problem it is a
consumerist religion
all you need to do is eat come on you
know you don't need to practice anything
you just you know the truth you
are possessed of the truth and you vote
accordingly and you've done it
you post online it's a it's a very
simple
easy religion it's a religion for
posters it's religion
for the modern american
but it gives me hope because i know the
people are desperate for meaning
and if the right good magicians can come
along and actually provide
a valuable system a meaningful system
there'll be just as many
people that will follow that and i think
that that is a beautiful
potential a beautiful vision of the
world is one
where there are many uh new forms of
living
new communities based on new ideals
um that i think is the good ending
okay um laura you had a question
statement
yeah hi um i guess uh i've always kind
of struggled to understand how to
communicate symbolically
when people are inevitably going to
receive it in a million different ways
however they take it whatever their
preconditioning is um but i also
kind of feel that way when i try to
communicate with reason
people tend to just take it however
we're not always on the same um we're
not always on the
starting from the same position so i
wonder whether you think
it has anything to do with either of
those methods of communication or
whether that's just generally
unavoidable and um
also if you have any thoughts on how to
effectively communicate with symbolism
so um
you know half the battle is is
confidence
half the battle is um honestly believing
in what you do and that's part of the
trick of being a magician
in in speaking in symbols is that part
of you is like
this is [ __ ] what am i doing but
when you see
that it's effective [ __ ] then you
realize
well i'm actually doing something
important i'm actually doing something
that works
so i think it's a matter of how
confident are you
in those ideas that you're sharing you
know are you really speaking what you
feel what you think
or is it just trying to do it
you know you can't try to do it you
simply have to
give it and then they'll understand i
think if you can meet them
animal to animal that is the way to
effectively
symbolically communicate like if a if a
bird were singing with a weak voice
or didn't mean their song i'm sure they
wouldn't be understood either
there's a sense of animal magnetism in
the effective magicians communications
all right um david you had a question
yeah thanks peter um yeah i'm looking
for some
clarification um how much control
do you think people have in the genesis
of these powerful memes
like is there any authorship or design
involved or do you think these memes
just
evolve independently of any human
control
and that's a great question and that's
one of the most important
magical questions but i think that the
concept of synchronicity
and of necklands hyperstation
is the answer which is that these are
ideas that
lay dormant until the creator
the author happened upon it
unconsciously
so sometimes the you you might think an
author
made that idea up but really it had been
waiting
in wait to come out of them
um i mean personally i would say there
is never
an author it's just an author gets
divine inspiration they get possessed of
that power and they do it they make it
um even if it's perceived as as their
own creativity i don't know if it's
really possible
like i was talking about if the idea is
effective it's close to something old
so um maybe there's a little bit of
personal influence but the majority of
the influence is coming from
something impersonal
right that that seems like a kind of a
post-modern interpretation like the text
is generated independently of the author
like you
you don't have to take into account the
author at all when interpreting the text
and same for memes
in this case well i suppose it depends
on the context of the author um and i
because i would disagree i would say it
is a modernist
view which is that i am sharing in the
ideas of frasier
and jung who are both distinctly
modernist i mean they're predicting post
modernism
but they are asserting and i am
asserting a real
energy a real archetype behind it
and that the author is really possessed
that it is not a symbolic
i'm not speaking in a metaphor i do mean
literally
that that idea was laying dormant to
arise that it is not
um it is not as if the author and the
piece are separate
it is just that the relationship between
them is a
a a divine one which is even you know
traditional that's the traditional
viewpoint
so if it has something in common with
post-modernism it is because
that is something that post-modernism
was correct about
all right thanks so many more questions
but i'll give someone else a turn now
thank you and do you have to leave at
the hour chris
no i can go on as as long as you want
cool so
maybe uh 10-15 minutes after the hour we
have a bunch of questions in the chat
um the medic caper you had a question
yeah hello um do you think
symbols or memes uh have to contain
energy themselves or can they rather be
a mechanism by which potential energy is
unlocked within the viewer a good that's
a good question as well
um and i think the answer is in yoga
actually which is that the
the symbol the meme is a vessel for
energy
it is not the energy itself it exists to
contain it
um when we do yoga the idea is that our
body
takes on an archetypal form like this is
a form that is built into our bodies
and doing so is what um puts that energy
it allows that energy to
to kind of emanate from you it puts you
in contact with that energy
so there's a bit of both the meme has to
be a good vessel
but your body also has to connect
with that image to get that energy so
it's a little bit of both
okay yeah i mean i i think of it usually
as a stimulus response
that's which is a less uh
i don't know a less magical view of it
maybe but but there are there definitely
are like there's
things about the body that are stable
representations over
time and just a function of human
genetics even right
um i don't know if i'm allowed to make a
comment here
but i kind of want to um
so that whole thing about the book being
left open being dangerous
um because the symbol is so contagious
within it
but that sort of thing i'm always highly
skeptical of it um
i think that sort of claim is made
to make the symbol powerful to the
person who's reading the book
like it's not it's not actually the
symbol has this inherent power
it's that sort of magical claim
um it charges it with power by uh
manipulating the belief of the reader
that's that's my opinion about that sort
of thing
and this is the answer with all real um
all real questions of magic is if it
works then it's true
that's the test if it if a magical idea
doesn't work then it should be gotten
rid of
but i do think that it is true and i
think that memes are living evidence of
it that's what i would say
so i mean it gives us we have sort of an
ontological disagreement then because
um if it works it's true i mean that
works that
that to me that just makes magic applied
psychology
which i think it definitely is like
stage magic is applied psychology
i think all the occult stuff that's it's
i view it as applied psychology
um yeah whereas
we're saying that uh there's some kind
of supernatural force
or energy within the symbol is uh
that's a different thing right that is
psychology
that is jungian and reiki
i view it the same way but i just think
psychology is far stranger than most
think
all right um michael
you had a question
yeah yeah uh i was thinking a
performance i don't know if you're
familiar with
jonathan hates work around sacredness
and the human ability to hold things
sacred you mentioned that
when when you connect the meme deeply
emotionally you get upset and like the
human ability to get very upset when you
attack something that is sacred or the
opposite of
the human connection of actually uniting
people when there are
whole things sacred together like
symbols and religion has
certainly hijacked this ability
throughout the ages but how is meme
related to this ability the whole
thing's sacred
do we do we actually hold meme sacred
and what aren't there a lot of memes
that we don't hold sacred that they are
silly or
or convenient and stuff like that
well that's again the question of
proximity of locality
the cross as i was saying in the
beginning is a meme
the cross is a iconic
symbolic image that spreads christianity
as
does the fish the simple uh fish
that was drawn by the early christians
that is
the christian meme and i what i argue
christianity spread
through memes romans might have seen it
as ha
look at this cross you know in fact one
of the earliest pieces of
in fact the first ever depiction of
christ is a piece of roman graffiti
and it depicts a a man with the head of
a donkey
and it says this is the god alex
worships
it's the palatine cross so it was an
object of ridicule so when we look at a
ridiculous internet meme
that very well might be a religion
that's going to come out
yeah but i think like of course
the cross if i attacked you across a
brand new cross you feel very
attacked and humiliated and and this was
connected to your sacredness but
as i myself has done this been
very upset when someone attacked my
hobby or something like that and
felt disconnected didn't realize that i
hold my hobby sacred
but now that i realize this i don't feel
emotionally uh
attacked when someone attacked my hobby
anymore but so
can you cultivate this awareness that
the they're not actually attacking me
or my sacredness they just don't know
why and how i hold this sacred
yes but that's it that's extremely
difficult but that is certainly the goal
of
my idea of recognizing that memes matter
yeah thanks right
megan you had a question
uh hey thanks chris this has been really
interesting um actually you're you're
just talking about the exact content i
was going to ask you about
um that i was just writing about
interesting um
i wanted to um ask what your thoughts
are about um
uh when a symbol gets corrupted and its
meaning changes
and i think that the best example of
that is the cross because
um christians now see the cross very
very differently to how someone would
have seen it in 32 a.d
i mean i think in 32ad it's clear that
symbol represents a threat
um you will obey or this is what's going
to happen to you
um and i have a feeling that it still
retains that meaning um and perhaps
there is something in the symbol itself
like the way it's asymmetric um
if you i mean if you compare it with a
symmetrical
um four-pointed star or an eight-pointed
star which i think are both old symbols
um and they're symmetrical and maybe
that's a sort of as above so below thing
and then we've got this asymmetric cross
and it had that specific cultural
meaning of being a threat
um and then now we have it as a
christian symbol and it's about you know
maybe sacrifice or compassion or
something completely different but when
is that um
where does that old symbolism still fit
in with that
what would be your thoughts on that
that's what young brings that up
uh in a very big way that and that's
like almost you know one of his
burns on christianity is like you know
perhaps their cross
should have been more balanced perhaps
it should have been symmetrical
um it shows an imbalance in the
character in the denial of evil
the denial of evil as a part of god
and his work in answer to job is
basically to introduce evil back into
god
so the cross is most certainly it's
unbalanced
but beyond that it is it's a symbol of
torture it's a symbol of destruction
to the christian but it's also the
desire the you know martin
martyrdom was a memetic phenomena they
found out about christ like oh i'm gonna
do that
and then did it so
[Music]
what part of christianity remains is
really hard to say i think
i think it's almost gone and i think
definitely the reformation was
was pretty much the the loss of that of
what was left in an attempt to
rediscover it
but the church and its countless splits
and its its wealth of dogma
it blinds the christian to the cross
nietzsche's big point is that there was
only one christian
and he died on the cross and everything
after that has been
a misinterpretation of the life of
christ
so the cross in a way has come to
symbolize
the church more than it did christ and
it is that
i think that and it's so if you read
nietzsche it's a very early point
when the symbolism of the cross becomes
perverted
uh another really good example is the
the pentagram and the pentacle
the upright five-pointed star is
considered good
and the reverse is evil in the devil and
this is something that levi talks about
that that is how magicians
play you take a symbol and you turn it
upside down or you
turn it a certain way and you've gained
power you've done
something to it and affected the way
it's viewed
but the idea for for the
the pentagram is that upright the fifth
point
is your head that the four points of the
star are your limbs
and then reversed it's the penis or the
genitals which is why it's the devil it
is the genital
sexual um base devil
so it's very interesting to see how
these symbols are able to be
perverted and diverted into new forms
when we were interested about a few of
us in the comments there is about
christian fish as well
do you have anything you'd like to add
about that it's it seems really
interesting about the christian fish in
the age of pisces and um
i noticed a few years ago that john
podesta thinks the fish is quite
important
and when john podesta thinks something
is important i'm inclined to agree with
him and want to know what he's up to
with that um any interesting threads
there
so jung has a whole book about the fish
called
ion and so the two fish
the dual fish of pisces the one fish is
christ and the other is the antichrist
just as the cross is
imbalanced we only the the christians
only accept
one of the two fish and the other is
considered absolute evil
you know it's the absolute other so
and this is one of my thoughts there's a
really weird thought about conspiracies
is that um like there's one hopefully
this won't get us all [ __ ] up from
youtube and algorithms and stuff
but like there's one and this accuracy
is actually true like the
the bill gates um
vaccine has a has a compound called
luciferase
and my thought would be if there's
anybody who's a conscious conspiracy
theorist
today somebody who knows about them they
are
playing with symbols the same way a
magician who reverses the pentagram
is doing they they said so if it is if
it is podesta he would be
trying to embody that other fish um as
christ was the one fish
at the end of the aeon because we are at
the end we need the other fish to get
to get to aquarius so
any symbol that's dual and that part of
it's denied
it must be rediscovered and unified to
get past it
all right i have a few questions that i
i'd like to ask you um
and see if anything warms up in the
chats um
yeah what came to mind when you uh
answered the q a question
uh is is powerful people using this
technology um so we had alexander dugan
on last week uh and
dugan's into um you know uh chaos magic
or at least to some extent
and people said he's you know putin's
brain influences russian geopolitical
strategy and stuff and then russia
is obviously in information warfare as
most nature's
nation states are um so what
what do you think about these powerful
actors to to risk going to the
conspiratorial realm
uh what do you think of these powerful
actors actually using this technology to
manipulate minds i'm a big fan of dugan
i love dugan
um because it's important to he's he's
forthright just like rasputin
he was a public figure who was pretty
much just out there like yeah this is
what i do
that's a beautiful thing um but yeah
you'd have to be a fool to engage
in politics without a magician at your
side especially post
2016. um so
yeah absolutely i don't i i highly doubt
there are
any high up enough pr people
or anybody who designs logos or makes
films that is not aware
of jungian symbolism a lot of
a lot of authors are just very outright
about it
and it's good because if we could if we
could make these ideas
conscious in the population if there was
a psycho-educated population
much of the symbolism would fail and it
would be much more difficult for people
to manipulate it
because like we're pretty much playing a
game that's been played for hundreds of
years
if we could get everybody to read the
rule book you'd have to play a new one
and things would be much more
interesting
all right um so let's see we have one
more question
dan you had a question um on susan
blackmore who was on the stoa last week
as well
um so you're gonna mute yourself dan and
ask your question
yeah hey so what's your
main distinctions between your own
theory of mimetics
and suzanne blackmore's like the meme
machine
or dawkins definition or i don't know if
you're aware of daniel dennis
i haven't read any of i haven't read any
of them um
but my my theory of mimetics is based
in jungian archetypes
and burrows uh viruses
so i'm approaching it from a more
distinctly
archaic religious and occult
sensibility so if it happens to
correspond
with a more scientific um
or analytic rational viewpoint then
it shows that you know both are on to
the same phenomena
isaias you had a question i was
wondering if you
if chris you could give your
interpretation of the law of dilemma
for modern digital times and especially
now during the pandemic
that's a great question um and i was
thinking about this because i was
thinking about a christian
symbol today there is the idea of the
the straight and narrow path to heaven
and the highway to hell
and a lot of people desperately want
do what thou wilt to mean um
just you know speed on the highway to
hell and it's not that at all
um it is in fact the very opposite it is
the most
narrow the most difficult path
is to do what that will to do your own
will
is the most difficult imaginable thing
um and carly talks about this in magic
without tears like
every single decision has to be weighed
according to your own
personal moral viewpoint uh there is no
preset morality there is no ten
commandments
you have to in every situation see is
this my will like is this
the right thing i should be doing how
many people can do that
and on the internet my god um where it's
all manufactured to consent
every viewpoint every choice is
manufactured by somebody or another
it's very difficult and obviously i have
fun with the internet
i've made my my philosophical
magical career talking about it but it's
almost always just like this is pretty
dangerous
um but when you see me in the future
it's probably going to be me having fun
using these ideas to do exciting
magical operations um so
yeah to do the law to do what thou wilt
uh it certainly is not
it doesn't look like being addicted to
the internet it doesn't look like using
the internet much
outside of as a tool if it's not a tool
if it's a pastime you're already lost
cool um so i'll ask the last question
um i'm curious what you think
of any life stances or philosophies as a
way of life
or life practices or what some people
call psychotechnologies
could help like on board these memes
and neuter them of their hijacking
potential and
just to speak on sort of how i kind of
operate
uh so i'm a practicing stoic um and one
thing that's great about stoicism is
they're like
reframe game is pretty tight if you
follow the stoic algorithm
um and couple that with kind of somatic
practices um
like when i review memetic tribes i
allow them to kind of infect my body in
a way and feel what they feel
and so kind of map the content to the
emotional reality
but if i'm also afforded the meta
distance when i do that if you keep
doing the reframe thing
so i'm curious if you think there's any
kind of uh philosophies
or practices that are good for that or
superior
uh or more superior than others yeah in
my personal context
you know i use the tarot i use tarot
cards a lot
and i'm a big fan of stories narratives
if you can look at a meme and you can
recognize
what it arose from what it speaks to in
other people
because if you're really good at tara
you you can see
the presence of an archetype in
something external
because that's what the whole point of
reading is is like you take these images
these very old images and you say well
this relates to this in my own life
or this relates to this other thing and
if you just get really good at that you
get
really good at a simple um
symbolic language
you will be very good at things i think
it's unfortunate because you see a lot
of people they get really
into fiction they get really into star
wars or really into harry potter
or marvel and they understand the
narrative there
they might even do deep analysis of it
but they can't apply it to their own
life
because like i was saying about the
internet they don't use it as a tool
they use it as a pastime
they don't actually believe in it
when you have a narrative that you
believe in
which is what religion used to be you
can then use that
symbolic framework to take apart
everything else
uh and to not be easily swayed because
you think well this is just like this
so when you see those memes mocking and
it does it makes me cringe but when
people like
oh this political figure is just like
voldemort or this person was like
you know this was dumbledore or this
person's like darth vader
like it's a very very simple symbolic
calculus
but they're they're heading in the right
direction if they can really commit to
that
and think this world is structured like
star wars
they're going to be they're going to be
a pretty fair jungian because star wars
is is a directly jungian tale
if you could really commit to that you
could really understand that story well
you would you would do pretty well so
commit to a narrative
even if it's one that you you choose to
create or you choose to believe in
you can commit to that narrative and
then you can apply it everything and
everything else
that would be perfect that is the way
out understanding
symbolism in one context and applying it
elsewhere
what's your thought on do you know that
the satanic group i think it's the order
of the nine
angles i think and then they have um
in order for their initiation they have
something called insight roles where
they go into these extremist groups like
uh
islamic terrorist groups or neo-nazi
groups they just really embody them
in order to dismantle sort of the
intersubjective prison that
you know civilization provides to kind
of free their minds but then they leave
the group
do you think something like that is
useful with um going to these weird
uh eclectic places on the internet
that's a great point that's a very
important element in chaos magic you
roll the dice
you give um each face of the dice a
religion
or a cult and you roll it and every um
every week you pick a new one or every
day you pick a new one and you
wholeheartedly
commit and you act as if it is true
so and it is something that wilson
wilson talks about as well uh robert
anton wilson
so that is a very important part of
liberating your mind from methods of
control
when i say to commit to an idea it's
definitely
not a way of
being
tricked not duped but just committing to
it as a framework
like you don't need to live on a boat to
get across the ocean
like or i guess for a little bit you do
but you still get onto land again
like you don't need to live in an
illusion you just need to use illusions
as tools
very cool yeah one of the kind of
informal projects here at the stowe is
inviting all these strange chieftains
like
um you know we had john zurzan who was
like a confidant to the unit bomber at
one point we had
you know alexander dugan and just uh
like how tyson wagner said just to hold
complexity
uh and not you know collapse to any one
narrative
uh and then you know that could be
practiced so
that being said uh i think we'll end
here um
chris that was fun uh i think a lot of
people enjoyed themselves in the chat is
there any kind of closing thoughts
where we can find you anything um you
can learn more about what you're doing
um i would uh just check out my youtube
channel meme analysis
i do a lot there um i'm on twitter at
the god disc
and my girlfriend and i do comics we we
make art
and that is at aeonic comics on
instagram that is a
e o n i c aonnic comics
um so that is it like and also
i i don't just do the memes i have a
whole lot of this you know a whole lot
that i try to do with what i with what
i've built
so thank you all for watching and thank
you for coming to
talk thanks for great questions too
beautiful
uh so i'll close out in uh a moment but
chris thank you so much for coming to
store we'd love to have you back people
are asking already
for you to be a sense maker in residence
here um so maybe i'll circle back to you
on that
uh for upcoming events at the stoa
uh tomorrow we have a packed day uh
prerequisites for communitas uh miriam
uh martino uh she's a wee space
practitioner
in the whole integral of theory movement
and they're pretty uh um they got their
we space game tight
and so we're going to talk about the
inner work required to actually get into
communitas
so that's at 2 pm eastern time tomorrow
this should be quite fun and then we
have
integral leftist michael siegel coming
in to talk about the spiritual
mission of america and the anthropocene
uh you can uh
ours be there and our boy tyson wagner
uh if you're gonna meet yourself tyson
plug your event tonight and then
the one that's happening on thursday i
believe
oh yeah thank you um thanks chris this
was really good
uh the event tonight is flowing with
unknowingness so we practice freestyle
freestyle spoken word and rap that is as
a way of doing collective dialogue
and deepening our relationship with
uncertainty so it's a playful space
and um no previous experience is
required if you
uh just are intrigued and the idea of
freestyle is sort of intimidating um all
the more reasons to come it is for me
every time i'm always nervous
and then um on the 30th
oh and that event is at 8 30 eastern by
the way
on the 30th um cadell last kevin orros
and daniel dick three gentlemen
wrote a book together called sex
masculinity and god and they
explore a lot of interesting ideas about
the
um about gender gender theory um
and the future of sex masculinity and
god
um so definitely check that out that is
september 30th
at 10 30 a.m eastern thank you
that's that's a wednesday night thursday
um so you can check out uh our website
our patreon uh the sub stack and then uh
i don't usually plug the youtube channel
but we have a lot of like we have susan
blackmore that was mentioned here
um who's one of the the founders of the
medic scene we have dugan
check out pat ryan's dark star series if
you want some real esoteric meme stuff
apparently he
he claims that he launched milo and with
his uh alchemic ways so
uh definitely check that out all right
everyone chris
uh everyone today great questions thanks
for coming to stawa
and we'll we'll play some interesting
music on our way out